Preliminary Guide to the Kent Tenney Healy Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kent Tenney Healy papers
1918-1969
MS 653
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
26
(26 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, teaching materials, minutes, reports, and memoranda relating to various Yale University committees and departments with which Kent Healy was connected. As a specialist in transportation he was a member of a number of government committees, among them the National Resources Planning Board, the New England Council Transportation Committee, and the New Haven Traffic Commission. His subject files contain extensive printed and mimeographed material on railroads.
Healy, Kent Tenney, 1902-
Conditions Governing Access
The majority of the materials are open for research. As established by Yale Corporation regulations., student records in box 22 are restricted until 2041; grade books in box 24 are restricted until 2024.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kent T. Healy, 1970-1973.
Related Materials
See also the Historical Picture Collection (MS 713), Series III, A 148, 1-11, for eleven undated lantern slides re: Italian railroads and highways which were removed from the Kent T. Healy Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Kent T. Healy Papers cover the period of time that Kent T. Healy was a member of the Committee on Transportation of the Economics department at Yale. The first five boxes of the papers contain Professor Healy's correspondence mostly with his colleagues in the academic and business worlds. Most of the correspondence falls within the time span of the 1930's and 1940's. Also included in the collection are typed manuscripts and notes for Professor Healy's papers on various aspects of transportation, as well as student papers. Professor Healy's main transportation concern was with railroads, and boxes 12 and 13 contain information files on various national and foreign railroads. Boxes 15-17 contain folders from the Committee on Transportation, and the rest of the collection is taken up with reports from various organizations, mimeographed papers of Professor Healy's, and printed material such as books, pamphlets, and newspaper clippings.
Biographical / Historical
Kent T. Healy was born in Chicago on February 2, 1902. He received his B.A. from Harvard in 1921, and his B.S. in Electrical Engineering from M.I.T. in 1923. Healey was an assistant professor of transportation at Yale from 1928-1937, an assistant professor of political economy from 1937-1938, an assistant professor of economics from 1938-1940, an associate professor from 1940-1945, and the Thomas DeWitt Cuyler Professor of Transportation from 1945-1970.
Economics; Railroads; Transportation; Educators; Healy, Kent Tenney, 1902-; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Economics
- Inventory, 1918-1969
  - Personal correspondence, 1934-1953 (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence, 1953-1968 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, Circa 1933-1963 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: individual folders, M-W, Circa 1930-1935 (Box 3)
  - Yale departments and committees: correspondence, memoranda, reports
    - Bureau of Highway Traffic, 1942-1945 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Transportation
      General
      See also Box 26.
      - Correspondence, 1926-1944 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1944-1959 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1959-1968 (Box 5)
      - Minutes, 1924-1960 (Box 5)
      - Expenses, 1954-1960 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence re: Thomas DeWitt Cuyler Chair of Transportation, 1922-1932 (Box 5)
    - Economic History Program, 1962-1967 (Box 5)
    - Economic Department, 1952-1956 (Box 5)
    - Executive Committee of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Executive Committee of the Social Sciences, 1948-1951, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - National Policy Committee: correspondence, expenses, 1947-1952 (Box 6)
    - Social Studies Department, 1955-1964 (Box 6)
    - Statistics Committee, 1946-1958 (Box 6)
    - Survey Committee on Planning Studies, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
    - Tenure Appointments Committee in the Sciences, 1953-1963 (Box 6)
  - Non-Yale committees: correspondence, memoranda, reports
    - New England Council Transportation Committee, 1953-1955 (Box 6)
    - New Haven Traffic Commission, 1945-1950 (Box 6)
    - Transportation Council for the Department of Commerce, 1953-1954 (Box 6)
    - National Resources Planning Board, 1940-1941 (Box 7)
    - New York State office of Transportation, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
  - Subject files (with little organization)
    - Transportation, especially of coal and oil; Bituminous Coal Division, Dept. of the Interior (BCD); and Lend -Lease Administration: correspondence, MSS, notes, Circa 1928-1959 (Box 8)
    - Transportation, mostly railroads: MSS, notes, some student papers, Circa 1933-1956 (Box 9)
    - Transportation, mostly railroads: MSS, notes, some student papers, Circa 1933-1956 (Box 10)
    - Railroads: correspondence, printed matter, Circa 1930-1961 (Box 10)
    - Railroads: correspondence, printed matter, Circa 1930-1961 (Box 11)
    - Mostly railroads and BCD: reports, printed matter, Circa 1922-1963 (Box 11)
    - Mostly railroads and BCD: reports, printed matter, circa 1922-1963 (Box 12)
    - Mostly railroads and BCD: reports, printed matter, circa 1922-1963 (Box 13)
    - Mostly railroads and BCD: reports, printed matter, Circa 1922-1963 (Box 14)
    - Mostly railroads: mimeographed material (including course hand-outs), printed matter, some MSS and correspondence, Circa 1918-1962 (Box 15)
    - Mostly railroads: mimeographed material (including course hand-outs), printed matter, some MSS and correspondence, Circa 1918-1962 (Box 16)
    - Mostly railroads: mimeographed material (including course hand-outs), printed matter, some MSS and correspondence, Circa 1918-1962 (Box 17)
  - Papers concerning the application of the Chicago, Burlington & Quincy Railroad Company before the Interstate Commerce Commission: correspondence, MSS, printed matter, Circa 1941-1950 (Box 18)
  - Papers of students, Circa 1932-1969 (Box 19)
  - Papers of students, Circa 1932-1969 (Box 20)
  - Printed theses, reports, miscellaneous, 1925, 1946-1947 (Box 21)
  - Student confidential
    - Letters of recommendation, correspondence with students, papers concerning fellowships, Circa 1928-1965 (Box 22)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Student files are restricted until January 1, 2041 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - Strathcona Interview Trips: correspondence, 1929-1934 (Box 23)
    - Grade books, Circa 1936-1948 (Box 24)
      Grade books are closed until January 1, 2024 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - New England Steamship Company: notes and charts, 1935-1936 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous Yale papers (oversize), mostly concerning Committee on Transportation, 1926-1929 (Box 26)